so let's start now discussing about processes
and threads if you think about the reasons
why you would like to have processes being
executed as multiple threads a very simple
example we can start with is that of the word
editor when you use a complicated piece of
software like Microsoft Word in this example
you do different things you are typing characters
while you type these characters they appear
on the screen but you know that there is more
stuff happening in the back the spell checker
might be continuously checking whether what
you type is correct or not you might be printing
a document in parallel and so on now the question
here would be if only one process
can be running at each CPU core at one specific
point in time because we have context switches
why do we have multiple cores? and also how
is it possible that while the spell checker
is running I can still type characters instead
of being just blocked because the process
is doing something else for instance checking
what I type or printing a document and/or
checking if there are updates to download
and so on this is solved because we have multiple
threads that are executing the same process
don't think about threads like something that
is different from a process in fact what I
said during the last lecture about processes
is not let's say orthogonal to this discussion
what we discussed so far it's basically executions
in which there is a mapping between one process
and one thread a thread is just the sequence
of instructions that belong to a program and
that you running one after the other so if
you assume that one process has only one thread
it means that when you execute this process
you can only run one instruction at the time
and which one you run depends of course on
the text section and how the code is organized
when you have a multi-threaded execution it
means that you can run multiple lines of code
that belong to the same process at the same
time in parallel at different cores notice
that it also means that you can context switch
between one thread and another thread when
these two threads belong to the same process
so you can run instructions that are about
the spell-checker of Word but then do a context
switch and run instructions that are about
the feature of Word that checks for updates
or the one that is reading your characters
and printing them to the screen simply put
you have multiple program counters and each
one is referring to the next instruction that
will be run for the same process this I mentioned
the very first time you have trade-offs in
space and time complexity and when you improve
one you usually pay higher price in the other
if each process is single-threaded then the
entire information that you keep for the process
and about the process at the operating system
level it's unique if you have multiple threads
that can run the same process then some information
that is specific to the thread needs to be
duplicated as I am showing here with for example
dedicated registers or dedicated stacks for
the variables of the functions you are running
or the next function that should be run and
so on in practice most modern applications
are multi-threaded and multiple threads run
within each application here you have some
examples again about Microsoft Word but you
can make examples with many other programs
the reason why we use multiple threads is
because it takes less time it's lighter to
create a new thread that belongs to a certain
process then it is to create a process because
when you create a new process you need to
create all the information about the process
since threads share information they don't
need dedicated information about the entire
process when you create a thread it takes
less time so it's more efficient and this
can simplify code and increase efficiency
the common example you have here is that of
a multi-threaded server architecture if you
write a server that is listening for requests
basically it is waiting for someone to connect
and then ask for something you can implement
this with multiple threads you can have a
thread that is listening and whenever someone
connects to ask something to the server then
you can spawn a new thread and tell to that
thread to execute the portions of code that
are related to how you check for the answer
how you produce the answer and have the listening
thread going back to listening again for the
next request this allows for responsiveness
because the listening thread is always listening
it takes very little time to start a new thread
to answer while going back to the next question
and if you look at the benefits of multi-threaded
applications you have responsiveness resource
sharing economy and scalability and they are
described in this slide
you do'nt need a multicore architecture to
justify the existence of threads even if you
have a computer with a single core you might
still want to have threads so that while a
certain part of the process is waiting because
it has to do something with the disk you can
run another part of the process that might
interact with the user for example the second
thing is that if you want to use a multicore
architecture you don't necessarily need threads
you can have single-threaded processes and
I am not talking here about the fact that
you can run different processes like Word
on one core and Spotify on another core you
can actually write programs like the example
I made last time for Google Chrome in which
you spawn several processes and then you have
these processes communicating with inter-process
communication since they are different processes
they can use different cores so is not that
if you want to take advantage of a multi-core
architecture you need to have threads or multi-threaded
processes